Heat.
Well, good morning everyone and welcome
to the Fiber Broadband Association's
Fire for Breakfast. We're now in our
seventh episode of 2026, the gold
sponsor for fiber for breakfast and his
conducts. While Congress is in recess
this week, today marks the fifth day of
the Homeland Security shutdown. You
know, fortunately, the federal agencies
that we've worked closely with, such as
F, the FCC and NIA, are not affected.
You know, last Thursday, February 11th,
NTI hosted their first listening session
on potential allowable uses of bead
non-employment funds. Over a thousand
participants attended and several FBA
members and allies spoke on our
priorities, including streamlining
federal, state, and local permitting,
investing in robust workforce programs,
and supporting adoption efforts. FBA
plans to attend NTI's new second
listening session today, February 18th,
and will continue to elevate our members
priorities and uses of non-employment
funds. On last Friday, the House
released the farm bill text. While we're
pleased to see the Rural Utility Service
Organization uh codify into law the
increased speed standards, we remain
hopeful that the future efforts will
emphasize the importance of symmetric
high-speed connectivity for rural
communities. FBA's been a strong
supporter of the bipartisan reconnecting
rural America act introduced by senators
Marshall Welsh and representatives nun
Vquest and Sorenson in the house that
would require our US programs to adopt
symmetrical speeds. Chairman Thompson of
the House Agriculture Committee is
aiming to mark up the bill on Monday,
February 23rd.
As a reminder, the Fiber Broadband
Association will be hosting its annual
public policy summit and flyin in DC on
Tuesday, February 24th, the same day as
the State of the Union, and we'll have
our fly in on the Hill the following day
on the 25th. And at our summit, um, our
members will hear from chairman Richard
Hudson from North Carolina, beat
champion Senator Shelby, excuse me,
Senator Shelby, that's Alabama, Senator
Shelley Moore Capital of West Virginia,
uh, FCC Commissioner Olivia Trustee,
Broadband Leader, Congressional Woman
Jennifer Mlelen from Virginia, NTI Chief
of Staff Brooke Dunelan, Speaker Mike
Johnson from Louisiana's policy advisor
Cyrus Arts, and Chief
Washington correspondents from the New
York Times, Carl Host. So, um I hope you
guys can join us. It's going to be a
great event and um we'll be there next
week. Last week on Fiber Breakfast, our
guest was Dr. Tamara Holmes, the
director for the office of broadband at
DHC
um in Virginia provide update on
Virginia's fiber projects and
initiative. You know, Dr. Holmes, great
friend of FBA, discussed the tremendous
progress that Virginia has accomplished
in connecting their states with funds
from state and federal programs. If you
missed that, you can go to our website
and see the replay. Today on Fire for
Breakfast, our guest is Michael Thomas
of Network Connects to discuss the
hidden infrastructure behind AI and
hypers scale networks. Michael is the
regional vice president of integration
services where he's responsible for
overseeing the ISP systems installed
across multiple disciplines and scopes.
During his more than 30-year tenure in
networking industry, he's managed inside
and outside plant technical teams,
engineering teams, vendors, call
centers, inter department relationships,
purchasing, budgeting, and planning. Uh
Michael served in the United States Air
Force. So thank you Michael for your
service. Then he moved into it in 1992
for a private firm. and then joined
Southwestern Bell Telephone, a name I
hadn't heard in a while. Now AT&T for a
24 year run. So I guess 30 years was 24
years. So I guess Michael, you have 54
years of uh experience. Wow. Um so a
bachelor degree. Michael's like 150
years old if you hadn't noticed that.
Michael has a bachelor degree in
business management information
technology from Western Governor
University. So with that, welcome
Michael. And for audience, please type
in your questions as we go.
>> Thanks. Appreciate it very much. Gary,
thank you for the introduction. And
yeah, not quite 150, but yeah, that 24
wide laid into that 30 plus for sure.
>> Okay,
>> all right, we'll let you kick things
off.
>> All right, cool. So, I just wanted to um
start talking about ILAS really quick.
So, this has been kind of a hot topic of
discussion and and it really kind of
aligns with the hyperscalers like we
were talking about before and and you
know, just to kind of give you guys an
idea right now, I'm in Abalene, Texas,
uh where this uh project Stargate has
gone this huge AI build and I have we
have teams out here that are actually
doing the the builds and we have teams
connecting these things together with
the ILAS turning up the circuits where
we connect these data centers together,
right? So, it's a a critical part of how
this goes. And we'll get into like how
those things work here in just a second.
The when we lay out the fiber itself, I
mean, when they lay out the fiber
itself, they have to amplify that
signal. And that's what the ILA is. It's
an inline amplifier, which is typically
located in a hut just like these that
are shown here on the shelter. We uh at
Network Connects, we build these things
out and we plan them and and help do uh
design and all that stuff as well. Then
there's just different stages of that.
So just kind of a real quick rundown of
what this critical component of these
things are um and what it takes to kind
of build them. So these are what typical
uh double-edge shelters actually look
like. These are a couple we placed
recently. Uh if you go ahead and change
the slide.
Now the key components here are we got
to figure out kind of where and how
we're going to implement these things.
So the wear is you know the fiber fiber
as it as it goes you're shooting light
down the fiber you have attenuation or
loss right and we've overcome that in
the past by regenerating signal. Um
that's where you take the light you
transfer it to electrical signal and you
recreate the light signal and retransmit
it. That creates an entirely new clean
signal. Uh but the problem is that
transition is channelized and it takes
time and we have enormous amounts of
bandwidth that we're trying to uh
transport. we can't get into that. So,
what they've done is come up with some
technology that was from back in the 50s
and kind of perfected in the late 80s,
early 90s where we amplify the light
kind of in an analog sort. We insert
photons,
it amplifies the light. So, that
amplifies the signal and it also
amplifies the noise, right? So, that's
where the ILAS come in. They have to be
uh a certain distance apart because of
kind of a a a noise budget, right? or a
loss budget rather um over overdo
because if you amplify signal and you
amplify noise, you let that noise and
signal get too close together, you
amplify them both, that noise just keeps
stepping all over your signal. So,
you're going to keep them close enough
together where your signal level and
your noise level are far apart so that
that delta is amplified as well. So, you
don't have to worry about u noise issues
as you go forward. So, as you can see on
here, there's a map with a green line
that just shows like a typical fiber
route and in a circle along this route.
Those circles are a general area and
they're roughly about 50 miles apart.
Right? The loss budget for attenuation
is about 23 dB as a not to exceed uh and
that roughly equates to about 80
kilometers or 50 miles 50 miles. Um it's
not an exact science. they can be placed
a little bit closer or a little bit
further away from the other one than
they have to be. It just kind of needs
to be in that budgeted area. Once they
set it down, they actually uh come back
and then we look at the actual design
for the inside and of these things and
how that's going to look with the number
of fibers that they're going to be
using. You know, where it's going to be
located, what the climate is and all
that stuff. Um, so we actually have
those things engineered. We do all this
stuff internally, but we have that all
that planning and engineering done. Um
go ahead and uh hit the hit the next
slide there. So uh part of our once we
actually have these things identified
and they pick a piece of land, buy the
land, we go out here and actually do the
construction on it that we have civil
workers. We go out here and make these
things actually happen from the middle
of nowhere. Uh go ahead and hit the next
one. Once we set the things uh set the
foundations down, we come in and
actually set the shelters down. A lot of
these things are preconfigured in a lot
of ways on the inside as much as we can
and externally to prevent amount of time
out in the field getting these things
installed um and really getting really
efficient about putting them in. But
this is just some pictures of actually
how you know we take and crane these
things over. They join them and then you
know put them together. And then the
last one there
is the internal fit out. So, um, there's
various configurations of this, but in
in in all reality, we're talking about
we're talking about a mini data center,
right? A little mini colo data center
that's sitting out in the middle of
nowhere that runs between 17 and 200
racks, kind of depending on what the the
use case is and what the customer's
needs are. And we engineer all of that
and and get all this stuff installed.
And these, you know, a lot of these
right here, you're showing DC power.
That is the preferred power of choice on
a lot of these things as well. just for
the stability and kind of getting back
into that old telco type mentality with
regard to uh stable power and utilizing
the DC just because it's cleaner. Um
plus when you install it looks a lot
prettier, right? So, all right, that's
so really that's kind of the that's kind
of the whole rundown on really kind of
how we how they're implemented, right?
And it's a really kind of a high level,
you know, 30,000 foot view of that. Um
there are a lot of other factors that go
into that you know that we support. So
you know be happy to take any questions
on that itself. So
>> well Michael let's start with um you
know you're down in I'm trying I'm
picturing um uh the uh what is it Billy
Bob Thornton kind of uh scenario where
you're down man there in Texas at
Stargate. Um, so you guys are all living
in a big house and trying to So this is
a half trillion dollar project. Can you
describe
what Stargate is at at high level and
then kind of how these inline amplifier
huts are, how they're using that as part
of that project.
>> So Stargate is a very large campus
build. I believe it's the largest campus
build in the world, if not one of the
largest one in the world now because
there's so many going these days. But
it's uh multiple buildings that are
interconnected, right? And they have the
GP the GPUs that they're using for the
AI in these buildings, but they they're
they're just connected together, right?
So it's just like one massive computer.
Um where the ILAS come into play is on
campus, you've in these places, not just
here, but elsewhere, you have multiple
buildings that are interconnected with
fiber optics u on campus. Well, those
are very short, right? You don't need
any amplification or anything like that.
the loss budget on those is non-existent
because it's only going a few hundred,
you know, yards. When you go from here
to the next place over that's in, let's
just say Louisiana or in in Nevada or
wherever, that long haul fiber, that's
where that loss comes into play. So,
when you shoot that light to that out of
this facility to go to the next
facility, they run the fiber out.
They've got to put these amplification
shelters on that link the entire way
roughly every 50 miles to maintain the
level of signal to to get back and
forth. So now once those things are
there, it connects two of these campuses
together, right? And then it's just
going to turn into like this web of
campuses or camp eye turned together as
well.
>> So you know the biggest cable I've seen
is 6912. So, six 6,912
fibers. What comes into these ILAS?
>> O, it really it really varies. A lot of
times we're dealing with 864s. Um, it
just the 6912s.
I haven't seen one with those yet, but
I'm not saying that's not outside of the
realm of possibility of of coming into
them. Um but typically they're not that
large when going into these sorts of
things because the size of the huts
limit the amount of fibers you can
actually amplify uh just due to the
space and power required for the
electronics, right? And understand that
these things are in these small 24 by by
36 huts that have a very limited ability
to provide cooling capacity and they're
out in the middle of nowhere. there's
like a large power budget to spend power
money or money on power to get
three-phase power out to these places a
lot of times. So, it's it's pretty
interesting.
>> So, in these huts, um these are largely
um line amplifiers, right? So, this is
really just regenerating the optical
signal to transmit. So, there's not not
full of GPUs or anything like that.
You're not doing any
>> no
>> large language models or any kind of
generative AI.
>> No, don't. there's strictly
amplification and connectivity. There
has been some use case on on proposed
use case for edge computing but it would
not in in so far as I've seen there's
not has not been nor would there be any
AI uh GPU placements for example in
these
>> okay so this is not a distributed AI
data center but it's largely for just
being able to move as you connect these
large data set of campuses you're just
being able to regenerate the signals
about every you said every 50 miles
>> right and you got to understand too
we're talking about a power budget,
right? So power and cooling. If I if I
have these things have a limited amount
of power and cooling, I'm going to make
absolutely certain that it's doing the
task that it needs to do. If I use that
power and cooling for some other
function, I lose capacity on the ability
to amplify, right? So that's that's
where we need to make sure it kind of
stays into that. Now that being said,
there has been a lot of of chatter and
use case about providing potentially
connectivity to like uh rural ISPs and
WISPs and things like that or
communities where they have like this
band, you know, like I said, these
things are going through the middle of
nowhere or I say that well they're going
between large cities. So there's like a
lot of rural area. So in these rural
areas, they could actually have uh
potential connectivity points in there
where they could actually get
connectivity into that bandwidth that's
just passing right by them, right? I
mean, there's just a information super
highway written right through the middle
of it. So there's the potential of
tapping into that.
>> All right. So there's a whole whack of
um technical questions here. So
>> yeah, I see that
>> totally anything would happen. All
right. So this one comes from the
audience is are you running coherent
DWDM technology for the long haul
network?
>> So that's outside of uh that's outside
of my expertise. I'm going to be honest
with you. So that's in the uh technology
space for um how the electronics what
electronics are using and what they're
actually transmitting over the fibers
and and frankly while I'm very
wellversed in in integration and all of
that that's that's a discipline that I'm
not experiencing. What about the power
requirements for these um ILAS? So, what
what are you doing for off on-site
generation?
>> So, typically right now they're they're
relying on commercial power um for most
everything that they're doing. And the
power budget really varies depending on
what the size of the shelter is. And the
design of that and the implement or the
design and engineering of these things
actually begins at that power budget,
right? how many cabinets and how many
amps and all of that, that all drives
into what the power budget's going to
be. Once we establish what that is and
we get from the commercial power power
uh companies that then we turn around
and have uh generation on site for
failure, right? So, you have diesel
generators are primary. I've seen a
couple of gas generators, but there are
new technologies coming out for on-site
power generation that we're looking at.
I don't know a lot about them yet. just
started to kind of dig into it, but it's
really exciting that you could wind up
having potentially a natural gas or a
propane connection at a facility and
generate all the power you need for that
facility without any external um
connections whatsoever.
>> And then um I got a there's a bunch of
quantum questions here, but u have you
seen interest in higher capacity or
higher quality ILAS in support of
quantum networking equipment? Uh,
>> I have not heard of any quantum
equipment that's out there in the ILAS
themselves because they're typically the
ILA electronics. I don't want to say
that's old technology, but it was
developed in the 50s and the seven in
the late 80s when it was kind of
perfected and employed and then really
into the late 90s and 2000 before it
actually uh really got legs. Right. So
it's it's as far as like different types
of electronics that they're going to use
to do that. I'm not I'm not going to be
able to know not.
>> So when you you put the ILAS, you know,
you're talking about 50 80 miles apart.
What factors might push that distance
longer or shorter?
>> That's a good question. So the um when
we're when we're doing the site
acquisition for these things and
actually in that circle that I was
showing and kind of determining what
that area is going to look like the what
that where that thing is located is
really based on what land is available
for purchase. What does the land look
like? You know how much is it going to
is there power available to it? Is there
something that we can there's a lot of
factors that go into that, but it's
really just the physical land piece
itself and the ability to use that
within that circle or that budgeted
space.
>> So given you know this whole AI is
eating the world um are you seeing that
the designs of the ILAS have changed
much?
>> The designs in ILAS have not changed
tremendously. Um we are starting to see
um some some compression in like the
electronics and miniaturization. So
you're starting to have more, you know,
more power consumption per cabinet on
certain builds that were being asked
for. Um that sort of thing is is
starting to happen. I know that they're
they're looking at like hybrid types of
these. Um again the technology and the
electronics internally I'm not that
aware of but I do know that they have
hybrid um amplifiers that they can you
know shoot over longer distances and you
know higher density that sort of thing.
So there are changes that are occurring
um as we speak. It's it's just kind of a
very interesting space to be in. It's um
also kind of these things are kind of
going two different ways as far as our
size. We've had people coming in asking
for very small versions of these uh just
a few racks and then we've had them
coming in with a couple of hundred racks
looking for basically a little micro
colo uh data center build that would you
know that would suffice to their needs
for whatever capacity they had. Kind of
going back to your 6912 question.
>> You know another audience question is um
do you know the average dB gain when
adding a EDFA or a fiber amplifier?
uh that I don't know the actual average
on that. No sir.
>> So when you're um you know what what
technical innovations you know optics,
power efficiencies, automation do you
think will impact the ILA design over
the next five years?
>> Wow. So that's a lot, right? Um so the
fiveyear the five-year thing there's
going to be so much activity. Um, one of
the things that I can see happening is
is that there's going to be more of a um
more of a dependency on on-site
generated power, right? I think that's
going to become more of a a thing.
There's also alternative battery
solutions that are going to provide some
additional support that will lower
operational costs. And then I think this
as we start to see these things and
electronics improve, you might start to
see them spread apart a little bit more
or gain more bandwidth. um the types of
cooling that we use are going to have to
change to be able to support some of the
newer higher density electronics with
more power consumption. Um and again in
these small spaces that's a real
problem, right? You got to remember
these things are like these little huts
in the middle of nowhere. So you've got
four concrete walls and a backpack air
conditioner on there that's pretty much
dependent upon ambient cooling. So
there's no really directed cooling in
there, no containment. So those sorts of
things are going to have to start to be
a part of of what we do, right? Uh to
compensate for those things.
>> Do you you know today I I assume that
these are um largely just dedicated for
these hyperscalers. But given that these
huts are in rural America where you need
um access to mobile wireless and
internet and things like that, do you uh
see that that that these would expand to
provide internet uh interconnections
internet connections um interconnect
connections so that people
>> Yeah. So that wouldn't surprise me at
all. And I think that that's definitely
where um I think that's definitely an
evolution that is going to start
happening. I think that the um the
hyperscalers where they're driving it,
they're not really the only people doing
it. You've got, you know, collocation
companies are big into this as well. And
you got to think about it from their
perspective too, right? I've got two
data centers. I'm leasing space in each
data center. If I have an interconnected
fiber between the two where I can,
that's going to drive real estate in
both sides of my business there. You
know what I'm saying? So they so the
collocations are in that as well. Then
when you start getting collocators in
there then that kind of opens the door
more for interconnected services along
that route as opposed to just inside the
both ends.
>> Uh so lots of questions about holocore.
Are you mostly seeing single mode fiber?
Are you seeing any uh holocore demand
yet for those?
>> It's uh it's single mode right now. Um,
we have a team that handles that. Our,
uh, our fiber team led up by Shane
Abbott's actually running into all that
stuff. So, I don't, um, I don't have
optics into if they're switched over or
how much of the holocore they're using.
Uh, but for right now, I know that it's
mostly glass.
>> And when your fiber comes in, do you
guys um, are these all connectorized or
do you guys splice them all in? And then
are they in fiber crossconnect cabinets
or how does that all work?
>> That's a very good question also. So,
no, we have LOSP teams that run the
fiber in. Um, it's not
pre-connectorized. Everything comes in,
uh, cut it in, splice it in, throw it
into an LTX, and then demarcation panel.
Um, and then whatever, you know, whether
it's a colo the customers are, or if
it's the customer themselves, they have
access to that at that point.
>> Another uh question for the audience is
what does the capex look like on a
typical ILA build?
Wow. That's I mean it varies just as
much as as the size and capacity, right?
I mean you're you're talking,
you know, the smaller lower ends. I
mean, you could be looking at right
around, you know, uh close to a million.
You're looking at things that go
significantly higher depending upon the
size and scope and and all of that. And
also some of the some of the design
requirements and power requirements from
the like from the hyperscaler customers
to to the implementation uh customers
that we have are um a lot right and and
those things can drive significant
expense. We've had I've had an instance
where we've had just the just the
battery portion of it was was well over
a million. Right. And it's so there's
like I said, it's just it's so broad. It
really kind of depends on a use case.
And um the best thing I would just say
is you just need to contact you know us
or somebody that has experience in in
consulting on these so you can get an
idea of what that's going to look like
for your company if you if you need to
have something done like this.
a lot of uh monitoring questions that
have come in like a fiber alarm
monitoring, you know, what's deployed
typically in the site and just overall
birectional monitoring. Uh so can you
talk a little bit about your fiber
monitoring?
>> So the fiber monitoring is all really
typically on the customer. we don't
really deal with that uh or the
electronics portion of that or I don't
necessarily but um there is uh we do
build into these things um SCADA and
also alarm access and you know all of
the stuff that they're going to need to
have um connectivity to be able to see
whatever it is they want to see at any
level.
>> All right, so here's one that's um
where does your responsibility start on
the DC property? Is it Zero Vault or in
the DC meet room?
>> Oh, that's a very good question. The DC.
So,
there's a meet me room. Um,
all right. So, I'm trying to All right.
So, it depends on the scope that we're
dealing. So, if we're if we're actually
doing the turnups on these things and
and understand my team goes and we do
the builds on them, you know, we've uh
we've got groups that do the all of it
and my team does all the inside plant
portion of it. So, they go build out the
inside portion and then I have another
team that goes and turns up the circuits
on, right? So, those guys will be going
into the DC meet room, right? That's
where that's where they'll go from to
turn those up.
Well, um, Michael, just a lot of
information here, a ton of questions.
So, um, this is definitely an area of
interest. U, so, if you're laying out
these huts every 50, 80 miles, that's a
lot of, um, right away. Uh, how do you
guys are you able to find spots that you
can put these? What's the footprint of
these? And, and how difficult it is to
be able to stand route and drop putts
every 50 miles?
Yeah. Well, it's it can be challenging,
right? Um, so man, so you got Billy Bob
Thornton. That's it, right?
>> For real. So, it's it's really a um
you know, I just lost my train of
thought there. All right. So,
every 50 miles, right? So, you're gonna
have to ask me that one again. I'm
sorry.
>> Oh, just about being able to get um a
place to drop your huts. So, you're
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Sorry.
Yes.
>> Right aways. So,
>> right. So, the so placing all that stuff
comes from our actual engineering team.
So, we have professional turfs team that
actually puts out and does the OSP
engineering for the route. When they do
that, they design and then they say,
"Okay, this is the budget in the circle
where that's going to be." And then
those go to uh the site acquisition team
that they actually go and and do all of
that business where they they go find
all those places and and put them all in
there. I think I have commercial power
and all that stuff. So, yeah.
>> Yeah. So, they do they do make sure
Yeah. So, there's a few things that they
need to make sure that it has commercial
power, you know. Obviously, um and I'll
be honest with you, we've built them
we've built them on mountains and we've
built in in swamps, literal swamps that
are just water you wouldn't believe. So,
it it it when I say, you know, where
these things are going to be and all
that, it's it's literally anywhere.
So it's interesting uh last question is
or observation maybe you know when I was
in um Austin I guess last year or a year
before last uh you know they were they
had such a grid issue in the past that
they say you know no data centers no you
know we can't do anything on the grid
now it's you know with administration
change they're like bring them on bring
them on so are you guys seeing any
issues with um the grid in Texas to be
able to support the world's biggest AI
data center.
>> No, not not that I've experienced. Not
that I've experienced.
>> Well, Michael, thank you so much. Uh,
thank the audience for a million
questions. All great questions.
>> Um, slide just came up with our next
regional uh, Fiberconnect workshop. We
had an amazing one. Oklahoma City, the
biggest one we've ever had. Uh,
Indiana's ahead of on registration, so
you better get registered ASAP. You
don't want that to be sold out on you.
That's in March 19th and then come fly
fishing with me in Bosezeman in July.
But thanks everyone. Uh Mike, thanks for
sharing your insights, expertise on
ILAS. And I look forward to getting back
together next Wednesday. We're going to
have our good friend Ernie Falconee of
the California PUC is going to be
discussing broadband competition and
pricing strategies in California's urban
market. So, uh, they just la dropped a
study that showed basically when you
have, uh, more than one gigabit
provider, um, across California, it
would save, um, consumers over a billion
dollars a year in their broadband
service. So, bring on all the gigabit
providers. Thanks everyone. We'll see
you guys next Wednesday.